PG 570, Connecticut Military Portrait Collection
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut military portrait collection
circa 1860-1959
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut State Library (collector)
5.75 cubic feet
This collection combines both group and individual portraits of Connecticut soldiers and veterans. A number of Connecticut National Guard, Putnam Phalanx, New Haven Grays and World War II portraits are included in the Collection, but Civil War veterans predominate.
PG570
Multiple
Scope and Content
This collection combines both group and individual portraits of Connecticut soldiers and veterans. A number of Connecticut National Guard, Putnam Phalanx, New Haven Grays and World War II portraits are included in the Collection, but Civil War veterans predominate.
Approximately 600 portraits are in the collection.
Related Material
PG 850, Cartes de Visite.
The Cartes de Visite include many individual portraits of Civil War soldiers.
Other Finding Aid
A portrait index available at the History and Genealogy reference desk lists individual names.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Connecticut Masonic Veterans Association; Connecticut National Guard; Military Order of Foreign Wars of the United States; New Haven Grays (Military unit); Putnam Phalanx; Civil War -- Veterans; Soldiers -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Photographs
Restrictions on Access
Accession 2012-047 is restricted due to its fragile condition. Contact State Archives staff for assistance.
Items in map case are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The source of most of the Civil War portraits was probably George Q. Whitney (RG 069:023). He is included in several group portraits and his name appears on the reverse of a few pictures. Since there were many individual donations to the collection it is impossible to determine what originally belonged to Mr. Whitney. Accession 2012-047 was donated by Phil Devlin to the State Library in 2011.
Accruals
Boxes 1 and 2 are Accession T001867. Boxes 3-6 are Accession T002670. Accession 2009-027 is stored with oversize items in the map case. Accession 2009-038 is stored with accession T001867 in Box 1. Box 7 includes Accession 2012-047.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Collection, circa 1860-1959
  - Connecticut Masonic Veterans Association, 1880 (Box 1)
  - Connecticut National Guard, 1887, 1914-1917, 1953-1959, undated; 25 items + 2 photostatic copies (Box 1)
    Accession 2009-038 is stored with accession T001867. It contains 15 photographs, 1953-1959. One group of photographs is of the return of colors of the 43rd Divisin to Connecticut, August 13, 1954. Gov. John Davis Lodge is pictured. Another group of photographs are of a military ball, February 11, 1956, with Gov. Abraham Ribicoff pictured.
    Additional items in map case.
  - Connecticut National Guard. 1st Connecticut Infantry Company K, circa 1880-1889, 1914-1918; 13 items (Box 1)
  - Military Order of Foreign Wars. Connecticut Commandery, 1919, 1923; 2 items (Box 1)
  - New Haven Grays, undated; 4 items (Box 1)
  - Putnam Phalanx, 1859, 1897, 1901, undated; 5 items (Box 1)
    1859 item is photostat.
  - Civil War Veterans
    - 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 7th, 8th Connecticut Volunteer Infantry, circa 1880-1914; 7 items (Box 2)
    - 13th, 20th, 25th Connecticut Volunteer Infantry, circa 1885-1913, undated; 8 items (Box 2)
      14th in bound volume at bottom of box.
    - 14th Connecticut Volunteer Infantry, before 1918; 1 album (14 photographs) (Box 2)
      Mostly taken at Antietam and Gettysburg.
    - 2nd Connecticut Heavy Artillery Association, 1896; 3 items (Box 2)
    - G.A.R. Dept. of Connecticut, 1883-1951, undated; 17 items + 1 photostat (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified groups, undated; 7 items (Box 2)
    - Unidentified tour group at Devil’s Den, Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, circa 1897; 1 black-and-white photograph; 2012-047 (Box 7, Folder Item 1)
    - Individual portraits (Box 3)
      - 1st Regiment Connecticut Volunteer (Box 3)
      - 1st Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Cavalry (Box 3)
      - 1st Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Heavy Artillery (Box 3)
      - 1st Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Light Battery (Box 3)
      - 2nd Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Heavy Artillery (Box 3)
      - 7th Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Infantry (Box 3)
      - 8th Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Infantry, 1 album (Box 3)
        Includes comrades of Major Andrew M. Morgan. A list of the contents of this album is available at the History and Genealogy Reference desk.
      - 9th Regiment Connecticut Volunteer (Box 3)
      - 12th Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Infantry (Box 3)
      - 13th Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Infantry (Box 3)
      - 15th Regiment Connecticut Volunteer (Box 3)
      - 16th Regiment Connecticut Volunteer, A-H (Box 4)
      - 16th Regiment Connecticut Volunteer, I-W (Box 4A)
      - 17th Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Infantry (Box 3)
      - 18th Regiment Connecticut Volunteer Infantry (Box 3)
      - 20th Regiment Connecticut Volunteer (Box 3)
      - 20-25th Regiments Connecticut Volunteer and unidentified (Box 5)
  - Connecticut World War II Soldiers (Box 5)
    Additional item in map case. This item is accession 2009-27, Co. A 11th Training Battalion, Camp Wheeler, Georgia, 1941.
  - Connecticut National Guard, 4th Regt., Co. E (Box 6)
    Album of 65 unidentified portraits.